<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss  xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" 
      xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" 
      xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" 
      xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" 
      version="2.0">
<channel>
<title>INQS</title>
<link>www.inqs.info/blog.html</link>
<atom:link href="www.inqs.info/blog.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
<description></description>
<generator>quarto-1.3.450</generator>
<lastBuildDate>Tue, 31 Jan 2023 08:00:00 GMT</lastBuildDate>
<item>
  <title>Wellness Plan Spring 2023</title>
  <dc:creator>Isaac Quintanilla Salinas</dc:creator>
  <link>www.inqs.info/blog/2023-01-27-wellness-plan-spring-2023/index.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 



<section id="areas-of-improvement" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="areas-of-improvement">Areas of Improvement</h2>
<p>Before designing a wellness plan, I need to assess all areas of my life and see what I can improve. Below is a list of areas that are important to me:</p>
<div class="columns">
<div class="column" style="width:40%;">
<ul>
<li><p>Mental</p></li>
<li><p>Emotional</p></li>
<li><p>Social</p></li>
<li><p>Spiritual</p></li>
</ul>
</div><div class="column" style="width:60%;">
<ul>
<li><p>Physical</p></li>
<li><p>Environmental</p></li>
<li><p>Financial</p></li>
<li><p>Career</p></li>
</ul>
</div>
</div>
<p>While there are many other aspects of my life that I would like to improve on, this is a good starting point for this semester.</p>
</section>
<section id="goals" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="goals">Goals</h2>
<p>Looking at the areas that I want to focus on, I want to create realistic goals. Additionally, each goal can satisfy multiple aspects of my life. I will use SMART goals to ensure <a href="https://www.ucop.edu/local-human-resources/_files/performance-appraisal/How%20to%20write%20SMART%20Goals%20v2.pdf">SMART</a> goals to make sure I create achievable goals. The period for all the goals is the Spring semester.</p>
<div class="tabset-margin-container"></div><div class="panel-tabset">
<ul class="nav nav-tabs"><li class="nav-item"><a class="nav-link active" id="tabset-1-1-tab" data-bs-toggle="tab" data-bs-target="#tabset-1-1" aria-controls="tabset-1-1" aria-selected="true">Goal 1</a></li><li class="nav-item"><a class="nav-link" id="tabset-1-2-tab" data-bs-toggle="tab" data-bs-target="#tabset-1-2" aria-controls="tabset-1-2" aria-selected="false">Goal 2</a></li><li class="nav-item"><a class="nav-link" id="tabset-1-3-tab" data-bs-toggle="tab" data-bs-target="#tabset-1-3" aria-controls="tabset-1-3" aria-selected="false">Goal 3</a></li><li class="nav-item"><a class="nav-link" id="tabset-1-4-tab" data-bs-toggle="tab" data-bs-target="#tabset-1-4" aria-controls="tabset-1-4" aria-selected="false">Goal 4</a></li><li class="nav-item"><a class="nav-link" id="tabset-1-5-tab" data-bs-toggle="tab" data-bs-target="#tabset-1-5" aria-controls="tabset-1-5" aria-selected="false">Goal 5</a></li></ul>
<div class="tab-content">
<div id="tabset-1-1" class="tab-pane active" aria-labelledby="tabset-1-1-tab">
<div class="callout callout-style-default callout-note no-icon callout-titled">
<div class="callout-header d-flex align-content-center">
<div class="callout-icon-container">
<i class="callout-icon no-icon"></i>
</div>
<div class="callout-title-container flex-fill">
Goal
</div>
</div>
<div class="callout-body-container callout-body">
<p>I will spend at least 1 hour every day, Monday through Friday, working on research related to my dissertation.</p>
</div>
</div>
<p>I want to increase my research productivity for my own career goals. Additionally, working on this will help me through my tenure process.</p>
</div>
<div id="tabset-1-2" class="tab-pane" aria-labelledby="tabset-1-2-tab">
<div class="callout callout-style-default callout-note no-icon callout-titled">
<div class="callout-header d-flex align-content-center">
<div class="callout-icon-container">
<i class="callout-icon no-icon"></i>
</div>
<div class="callout-title-container flex-fill">
Goal
</div>
</div>
<div class="callout-body-container callout-body">
<p>I will learn how to create a new tea-related beverage at home each month.</p>
</div>
</div>
<p>This goal has the potential to serve three aspects of my life: Physical, Environmental, and Financial. Learning how to create new tea drinks will allow me to save money instead of buying them from different coffee shops. Additionally, I will know what ingredients are used in the drinks. Therefore, I will be able to improve the physical aspect of my life. Lastly, this will help the environmental part of my life by reducing my environmental impact and using less plastic.</p>
</div>
<div id="tabset-1-3" class="tab-pane" aria-labelledby="tabset-1-3-tab">
<div class="callout callout-style-default callout-note no-icon callout-titled">
<div class="callout-header d-flex align-content-center">
<div class="callout-icon-container">
<i class="callout-icon no-icon"></i>
</div>
<div class="callout-title-container flex-fill">
Goal
</div>
</div>
<div class="callout-body-container callout-body">
<p>I will travel to a new city in Southern CA each month and buy their local newspaper.</p>
</div>
</div>
<p>One of my main goals is to travel more globally and locally. I especially want to get to know small communities located in Southern California. For that reason, I want to make an effort to explore more of Southern CA. This goal has the potential to affect four aspects of my life: mental, social, spiritual, and physical.</p>
</div>
<div id="tabset-1-4" class="tab-pane" aria-labelledby="tabset-1-4-tab">
<div class="callout callout-style-default callout-note no-icon callout-titled">
<div class="callout-header d-flex align-content-center">
<div class="callout-icon-container">
<i class="callout-icon no-icon"></i>
</div>
<div class="callout-title-container flex-fill">
Goal
</div>
</div>
<div class="callout-body-container callout-body">
<p>I will go swimming two times a week for 30 minutes.</p>
</div>
</div>
<p>When I was planning to move to Camarillo, I wanted to start something new for my physical health. Therefore, I decided to start swimming.</p>
</div>
<div id="tabset-1-5" class="tab-pane" aria-labelledby="tabset-1-5-tab">
<div class="callout callout-style-default callout-note no-icon callout-titled">
<div class="callout-header d-flex align-content-center">
<div class="callout-icon-container">
<i class="callout-icon no-icon"></i>
</div>
<div class="callout-title-container flex-fill">
Goal
</div>
</div>
<div class="callout-body-container callout-body">
<p>I will go to the gym three times a week for 1 hour.</p>
</div>
</div>
<p>Similar to swimming, I want to develop new habits and exercise more. Developing this habit and going to the gym more will help my physical health.</p>
</div>
</div>
</div>
</section>
<section id="plan" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="plan">Plan</h2>
<div class="tabset-margin-container"></div><div class="panel-tabset">
<ul class="nav nav-tabs"><li class="nav-item"><a class="nav-link active" id="tabset-2-1-tab" data-bs-toggle="tab" data-bs-target="#tabset-2-1" aria-controls="tabset-2-1" aria-selected="true">Goal 1</a></li><li class="nav-item"><a class="nav-link" id="tabset-2-2-tab" data-bs-toggle="tab" data-bs-target="#tabset-2-2" aria-controls="tabset-2-2" aria-selected="false">Goal 2</a></li><li class="nav-item"><a class="nav-link" id="tabset-2-3-tab" data-bs-toggle="tab" data-bs-target="#tabset-2-3" aria-controls="tabset-2-3" aria-selected="false">Goal 3</a></li><li class="nav-item"><a class="nav-link" id="tabset-2-4-tab" data-bs-toggle="tab" data-bs-target="#tabset-2-4" aria-controls="tabset-2-4" aria-selected="false">Goal 4</a></li><li class="nav-item"><a class="nav-link" id="tabset-2-5-tab" data-bs-toggle="tab" data-bs-target="#tabset-2-5" aria-controls="tabset-2-5" aria-selected="false">Goal 5</a></li></ul>
<div class="tab-content">
<div id="tabset-2-1" class="tab-pane active" aria-labelledby="tabset-2-1-tab">
<p>Since I am struggling to keep my research productivity up, I will try new strategies. To get more research done, I plan to work on research as the very first thing I do when I get into my office. If I complete this task at the beginning of my day, I will get it out of the way and focus on things that are easier for me. The idea is to do the things I struggle with at the very beginning of my day.</p>
<p>Additionally, I plan to use the <a href="https://www.forestapp.cc/">Forest App</a> to maintain my focus. I will do a 20 minute session of writing<sup>1</sup> and then do a 10 minute break. I will repeat this process until I complete an hour of writing.</p>
</div>
<div id="tabset-2-2" class="tab-pane" aria-labelledby="tabset-2-2-tab">
<p>Right now, I am working on learning how to make a chai latte at home. So far, I have learned how to make oat milk how I like it. Next, I want to make chai concentrate using raw ingredients. I have bought many of the tools and feel ready to start experimenting with making the concentrate.</p>
<p>Other types of teas that I want to learn are hibiscus and Thai.</p>
</div>
<div id="tabset-2-3" class="tab-pane" aria-labelledby="tabset-2-3-tab">
<p>I first plan to visit Ojai in February. Depending on the weather, I want to visit Twentynine Palms for the <a href="https://sandiegoexplorer.com/california-wildflowers-california-superbloom/">super bloom</a>; otherwise, I will visit Carpinteria. Lastly, I want to visit Idyllwild. I want to visit a special event/festival for each location if possible.</p>
</div>
<div id="tabset-2-4" class="tab-pane" aria-labelledby="tabset-2-4-tab">
<p>Because I set this goal for two 30 minute sessions, I believe I can complete this task. It is easier to spend a quick 30 minute session than a full hour.</p>
</div>
<div id="tabset-2-5" class="tab-pane" aria-labelledby="tabset-2-5-tab">
<p>Similar to my research goals, I plan to go to the gym in the morning and get them done early so I can focus on other things I am interested in. I plan to go to the gym early every Monday, Wednesday, and Friday. This task will be before my writing sessions.</p>
</div>
</div>
</div>
</section>
<section id="accountability" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="accountability">Accountability</h2>
<p>There are two ways that I will try told hold myself accountable. First, I will share my wellness plan with friends and family members. Second, I will create an incentive plan for each goal I complete. I will reassess my goals before spring break (3/17/23) and adjust accordingly. Overall, I want to create consistency with these goals. Any positive gain will be a win. At the end of the semester, I plan to reflect on the process and see what worked and what did not.</p>


</section>


<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section id="footnotes" class="footnotes footnotes-end-of-document"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Footnotes</h2>

<ol>
<li id="fn1"><p>writing means any task related to research↩︎</p></li>
</ol>
</section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>Wellness</category>
  <guid>www.inqs.info/blog/2023-01-27-wellness-plan-spring-2023/index.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 31 Jan 2023 08:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="www.inqs.info/blog/2023-01-27-wellness-plan-spring-2023/CI.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>SMART Program</title>
  <dc:creator>Isaac Quintanilla</dc:creator>
  <link>www.inqs.info/blog/2021-05-03-smart-program/index.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 



<section id="introduction" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="introduction">Introduction</h2>
<p>At the beginning 2020, I learned that there were several undergraduate students interested in attending graduate school. However, many of them had the idea that they weren’t capable of succeeding in graduate school. This was nonsense! I TA’ed them through Regression and ANOVA courses and got to see first hand their capabilities. It was shocking to hear that they think like this. While I can go into details of my ideas why they think like this (possibly imposter syndrome<sup>1</sup>), this isn’t the post for it. I was set out to convince and prepare these students to apply to graduate school.</p>
<p>In the Spring Quarter of 2020, I decided to hold a virtual seminar in applying to graduate school<sup>2</sup>. The seminar focused on the application process and choosing the correct degree program. At the end of the seminar, approximately 15 undergraduate students attended, and we had a lively discussion between undergraduate students, graduate students, and faculty. It showed that undergraduate students were interested in pursuing graduate degrees. This motivated me to hold more events similar to this seminar.</p>
<p>In the Fall Quarter of 2020, I decided to hold a similar seminar for undergraduate students. However, I focused more on writing different statements as well as holding discussion at the end<sup>3</sup>. At the same time, my colleague sent me a tweet about a program from the University of Washington, the Statistics and Probability Association <a href="https://spa-drp.github.io/">Direct Reading Program</a>. It is an excellent program, and I decided to implement a similar program. Thus, the beginnings of the SMART Program was born!</p>
</section>
<section id="development" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="development">Development</h2>
<p>For the remainder of the Fall quarter, I began talking to other graduate students about creating a mentoring program within the department. I pitched them that they will mentor an undergraduate student for a statistical project. Many students seemed on board to participate in the program. Afterwards, I started asking Teaching Faculty to support the program. By the end of the quarter, I had an idea of the support I will get from the department.</p>
<p>Towards the end of the year, almost everyone had a rough winter due to the pandemic. Fatigued had set in to many students, and they needed time to rest. I myself struggled through the winter. It was challenging to rest during my break due to competing pressures. While I did manage to get through the winter, I did not want to add any extra pressure to the remaining graduate students that expressed interest in mentoring in the program. I decided to wait until half way through the quarter to begin asking graduate students for their commitment to the program. Fortunately, everyone was excited to be a mentor in the program.</p>
<p>At the same time, I was worried about having graduate students coming up with a project. I was afraid that students could not come up with an idea that was feasible for an undergraduate student to complete, so I decided to come up with a project that anyone can easily do. Thus the <a href="https://ucrgradstat.github.io/ucrstats/">ucrstats</a> package was born. The idea was for a mentor teach an undergrad about a topic, then the mentee can create a <a href="https://rstudio.github.io/learnr/">learnr</a> tutorial to teach other students. The only thing the mentor needed to do was gather materials and R code for the student to learn about the topic. The tutorials can easily be created using an RMarkdown file. At the end, the mentee will have a product that they can show off and put on their CV. It was a different type of project that focused on programming than the traditional form of research. Fortunately, all other graduate students had project ideas; however, this can be a good back up for those who do not have a project idea. Additionally, the package can be utilized from other graduate students in different departments who want to learn more about statistics.</p>
</section>
<section id="recruitment" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="recruitment">Recruitment</h2>
<p>We recruited undergraduate students for the program with an application using Google Forms. We asked for basic things such as what classes you took, write a couple of essays, and your interests in the projects.</p>
<p>Using all the information we gathered, we began the selection process. We ranked each student based on their interests, the classes they have completed, and how well they met the admission criteria. From their, we selected students based on their rankings.</p>
<p>Looking back at the application process, there are couple of things I wish we could have done a bit differently. First, I think we should ask for CVs or resumes. This way we can better learn about the student. Second, the application process should begin at least a month before the start of the quarter. We had to operate with some tight deadlines and I did not enjoy the pressure. Other than that I will need to consult with the current cohort for more recommendations.</p>
</section>
<section id="reflection" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="reflection">Reflection</h2>
<p>The SMART Pilot Program was launched in Spring 2021 with our first cohort of mentors and mentees. We held a small orientation with the mentees to set the expectations<sup>4</sup>. The remainder of the quarter went smoothly. There were a few bumps in the roads here and there, but most of it was providing guidance to the mentors. At the end of the quarter, we held a symposium where all groups presented their work.</p>
<p>Starting a program is tough! I worried about so many things. Mostly making sure both the mentors and mentees were progressing with their projects and gaining something the other time. However, I just needed to have faith that everything will go well. Fortunately, the pilot was a success! I was so impressed by everyone’s presentation, and I think we showed the department how capable both the graduate and undergraduate students are in completing a project. This was certainly a long process, but overall I am glad I started the program and excited to see where it goes from here.</p>
</section>
<section id="future" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="future">Future</h2>
<p>As I am writing this post, I am moving on to my sixth year of my graduate program, and I have my eyes on graduating and moving on the next phase of my career. That being said, I don’t really know if I will be involved for the second year of the program. I hope I inspired other graduate students to take on the mantle and continue the program. I truly believe the program is a great asset for the department. If I am around for the second year of the program, I will most likely take a consulting position to ensure that other graduate students can continue the program without relying on me. Otherwise, I will prefer to only coordinate for the second year.</p>
<p>As for the program itself, I hope the program will serve students from marginalized communities. Particularly communities where Statistics has be utilized against them. We need better statisticians who constantly thinking about how their work can harm the most vulnerable. Those who will advocate for these groups and change the Statistics community for the better. My hope is that the program will train individuals who will advocate for a better future.</p>


</section>


<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section id="footnotes" class="footnotes footnotes-end-of-document"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Footnotes</h2>

<ol>
<li id="fn1"><p>Really the myth of imposter syndrome and more how Academia is designed only for the privileged.↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn2"><p>The seminar occurred at the beginning of the pandemic. My goal was to create some form of normal for the students during this time. However, other students may have found it difficult to concentrate during the quarter.↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn3"><p>The discussion from the first seminar was the most important part!↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn4"><p>I wised to have the mentors there as well but could not schedule everyone together.↩︎</p></li>
</ol>
</section></div> ]]></description>
  <guid>www.inqs.info/blog/2021-05-03-smart-program/index.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 10 Jun 2021 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="www.inqs.info/blog/2021-05-03-smart-program/LG5.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>RcppArmadillo</title>
  <dc:creator>Isaac Quintanilla</dc:creator>
  <link>www.inqs.info/blog/2021-04-20-incorporating-rcpp/index.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 



<section id="journey" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="journey">Journey</h2>
<p>When I first started using Rcpp for my research, I had no idea what I was doing. All I knew was that you can incorporate C++<sup>1</sup> code in your R scripts to speed up data processing. I did spend some time learning C++ through <a href="https://www.learncpp.com/">www.learningcpp.com</a>, but I didn’t get far because my example program did not go well. Troubleshooting the problem was a nightmare. However, it did give me an idea of how C++ programming looks like.</p>
<p>Once, I decided to implement C++ for my research, I focused on how to incorporate it in R. At the time, I had a fairly strong R background, and I knew you can use C++ in R via Rcpp. Therefore, I spent some time learning more about Rcpp from their <a href="http://www.rcpp.org/">website</a> and book. After reading everything I could, I didn’t learn much. It was really advanced and not written for a newbie. However, I did learn that you can compile a C++ function<sup>2</sup> that can be executed in R via Rcpp. The challenge was to build a cpp file that contained functions for my analysis. I turned to <a href="https://adv-r.hadley.nz/rcpp.html">Advanced R</a> by Hadley Wickham for more help.</p>
<p>Wickham’s book provided the necessary information to build basic functions to use in R. I learned how to write basic functions in cpp and making them executable with <code>cppFunction</code>. Additionally, the book covers the basic classes, looping, and function exporting. I felt prepared to write and use functions in R! However, my research required linear algebra, and it would have been a nightmare to program matrix multiplication with the basics. These challenges led me to <a href="http://dirk.eddelbuettel.com/code/rcpp.armadillo.html">RcppArmadillo</a>.</p>
<p>RcppArmadillo is designed to incorporate the <a href="http://arma.sourceforge.net/">Armadillo</a> library in R via Rcpp. The Armadillo library contains functions that make it easy to conduct linear algebra in cpp. Additionally, it isn’t difficult to learn the syntax. The library is implemented to closely follow Matlab<sup>3</sup> syntax.</p>
<p>After writing functions and troubleshooting problems, I was able to export my functions to R. Making sure everything worked, I ran the same data on both my R and cpp functions, and it worked! I was able to produce the same value for each function. It gave me the confidence that I would be able to complete my research.</p>
<p>After successfully implementing cpp in my research, I wanted to know how much faster was my code. Going back to Wickham’s book, there was information on benchmarking different functions. Using the <a href="https://www.tidyverse.org/blog/2018/06/bench-1.0.1/">bench</a> package to identify how long each function was taking to execute, I found my R function took 13 times longer than my cpp function. I was shocked! I knew cpp would make my code faster, but I didn’t expect it to be that much faster<sup>4</sup>. This convinced me that all my efforts were worth it!</p>
</section>
<section id="using-rcpparmadillo" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="using-rcpparmadillo">Using RcppArmadillo</h2>
<p>I like to keep my functions in separate scripts and source them from my main analysis script. Naturally, I have all my cpp function in a separate file. The first thing you will need to do is create a cpp file: <code>file_name.cpp</code>. The first lines in my files are given below<sup>5</sup>:</p>
<div class="sourceCode" id="cb1" style="background: #f1f3f5;"><pre class="sourceCode default code-with-copy"><code class="sourceCode default"><span id="cb1-1">#include &lt;RcppArmadillo.h&gt;</span>
<span id="cb1-2">#include &lt;Rcpp.h&gt;</span>
<span id="cb1-3"></span>
<span id="cb1-4">using namespace Rcpp;</span>
<span id="cb1-5">using namespace arma;</span>
<span id="cb1-6"></span>
<span id="cb1-7">// [[Rcpp::depends(RcppArmadillo)]]</span></code></pre></div>
<p>The first couple of lines indicates which header or standard files to be included for compilation. I like to think of them as the <code>library()</code> function in R. The next couple lines indicate the names for different libraries. Different libraries may have functions with the same. Namespace allows you to use functions with the same name but from different libraries. Similar with R’s <code>::</code> operator. The last line is used by the <code>sourcecpp()</code> function in R. It helps with library dependency.</p>
<p>Now we can create functions to be utilized in R. The code below calculates the mean in cpp:</p>
<div class="sourceCode" id="cb2" style="background: #f1f3f5;"><pre class="sourceCode default code-with-copy"><code class="sourceCode default"><span id="cb2-1">// [[Rcpp::export]]</span>
<span id="cb2-2"></span>
<span id="cb2-3">double mean_cpp(arma::vec x){</span>
<span id="cb2-4">  int n = x.size();</span>
<span id="cb2-5">  double x_sum = sum(x);</span>
<span id="cb2-6">  double x_mean = x_sum / n; </span>
<span id="cb2-7">  return x_mean; </span>
<span id="cb2-8">}</span></code></pre></div>
<p>The first line tells R to make the following function accessible to the user<sup>6</sup>. The remaining lines are the function itself. Creating a function in cpp is similar to R<sup>7</sup>. The main difference is that you need to specify the data types. Combining the two chunks together, your cpp file should look similar to the chunk below:</p>
<div class="sourceCode" id="cb3" style="background: #f1f3f5;"><pre class="sourceCode default code-with-copy"><code class="sourceCode default"><span id="cb3-1">#include &lt;RcppArmadillo.h&gt;</span>
<span id="cb3-2">#include &lt;Rcpp.h&gt;</span>
<span id="cb3-3"></span>
<span id="cb3-4">using namespace Rcpp;</span>
<span id="cb3-5">using namespace arma;</span>
<span id="cb3-6"></span>
<span id="cb3-7">// [[Rcpp::depends(RcppArmadillo)]]</span>
<span id="cb3-8"></span>
<span id="cb3-9">// [[Rcpp::export]]</span>
<span id="cb3-10"></span>
<span id="cb3-11">double mean_cpp(arma::vec x){</span>
<span id="cb3-12">  int n = x.size();</span>
<span id="cb3-13">  double x_sum = sum(x);</span>
<span id="cb3-14">  double x_mean = x_sum / n; </span>
<span id="cb3-15">  return x_mean; </span>
<span id="cb3-16">}</span></code></pre></div>
<p>In R, you will need to load the following packages<sup>8</sup>:</p>
<div class="cell">
<div class="sourceCode cell-code" id="cb4" style="background: #f1f3f5;"><pre class="sourceCode r code-with-copy"><code class="sourceCode r"><span id="cb4-1"><span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">library</span>(Rcpp)</span>
<span id="cb4-2"><span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">library</span>(RcppArmadillo)</span></code></pre></div>
</div>
<p>The next step is to compile your cpp file. You can do this with the <code>sourceCpp()</code> function:</p>
<div class="cell">
<div class="sourceCode cell-code" id="cb5" style="background: #f1f3f5;"><pre class="sourceCode r code-with-copy"><code class="sourceCode r"><span id="cb5-1">Rcpp<span class="sc" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">::</span><span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">sourceCpp</span>(<span class="st" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">"example_cpp.cpp"</span>)</span></code></pre></div>
</div>
<p>This will compile your functions and make them executable in R. You can now use your function like any other R function.</p>
<div class="cell">
<div class="sourceCode cell-code" id="cb6" style="background: #f1f3f5;"><pre class="sourceCode r code-with-copy"><code class="sourceCode r"><span id="cb6-1"><span class="do" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: italic;">## Generating Data</span></span>
<span id="cb6-2">Y <span class="ot" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">&lt;-</span> <span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">rnorm</span>(<span class="dv" style="color: #AD0000;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">1000</span>)</span>
<span id="cb6-3"></span>
<span id="cb6-4"><span class="do" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: italic;">## Using mean_cpp</span></span>
<span id="cb6-5"><span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">mean_cpp</span>(Y)</span></code></pre></div>
<div class="cell-output cell-output-stdout">
<pre><code>[1] 0.07524497</code></pre>
</div>
<div class="sourceCode cell-code" id="cb8" style="background: #f1f3f5;"><pre class="sourceCode r code-with-copy"><code class="sourceCode r"><span id="cb8-1"><span class="do" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: italic;">## Using Built-in mean functions</span></span>
<span id="cb8-2"><span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">mean</span>(Y)</span></code></pre></div>
<div class="cell-output cell-output-stdout">
<pre><code>[1] 0.07524497</code></pre>
</div>
</div>
<p>To see the speed gains, we can use the <code>mark()</code> function from the <code>bench</code> package.</p>
<div class="cell">
<div class="sourceCode cell-code" id="cb10" style="background: #f1f3f5;"><pre class="sourceCode r code-with-copy"><code class="sourceCode r"><span id="cb10-1">bench<span class="sc" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">::</span><span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">mark</span>(</span>
<span id="cb10-2">  <span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">mean</span>(Y),</span>
<span id="cb10-3">  <span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">mean_cpp</span>(Y)</span>
<span id="cb10-4">)</span></code></pre></div>
<div class="cell-output cell-output-stdout">
<pre><code># A tibble: 2 × 6
  expression       min   median `itr/sec` mem_alloc `gc/sec`
  &lt;bch:expr&gt;  &lt;bch:tm&gt; &lt;bch:tm&gt;     &lt;dbl&gt; &lt;bch:byt&gt;    &lt;dbl&gt;
1 mean(Y)       3.26µs    3.8µs   235815.        0B        0
2 mean_cpp(Y)   1.84µs   2.92µs   338610.    7.67KB        0</code></pre>
</div>
</div>
<p>You can see that the cpp function is much faster than the R built-in function.</p>
</section>
<section id="speed-gains-explanation" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="speed-gains-explanation">Speed Gains Explanation</h2>
<p>You may be asking why is R much slower than cpp. From what I can gather, R is an interpreted language while cpp is a compiled language. While I don’t really know what the difference is, it makes cpp much faster.</p>
<p>I like to think there is a difference of requirements. You need to be more careful with cpp because it does not convert inputs to the correct data type. R will do it automatically. Therefore, R takes more time to ensure everything is correct before computing a function. Cpp requires more thinking from the user, but will reward them with speed gains. I am sure there is way more to this simple explanation, but the end result is that cpp is much faster than R.</p>
</section>
<section id="next-steps" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="next-steps">Next Steps …</h2>
<p>As my research is progressing, I am noticing the need to incorporate different methods not found in the Armadillo library. For example, I want to incorporate the <a href="https://www.gnu.org/software/gsl/">GNU Scientific Library</a>. I learned there is an R package exists for the library, <a href="https://dirk.eddelbuettel.com/code/rcpp.gsl.html">RcppGSL</a>! This gives me hope that I can use it for my research. However, I want to use the Armadillo library alongside with GSL. This has a potential to bring new problems with data type incompatibilities. I have ideas for potential solutions, but I will need to test them out.</p>
<p>I also want to learn more about the capabilities of Rcpp. Specifically, what other functions does it contain. I learned that Rcpp has functions for distribution functions. This can be useful for expanding my research.</p>


</section>


<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section id="footnotes" class="footnotes footnotes-end-of-document"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Footnotes</h2>

<ol>
<li id="fn1"><p>I may write C++ as cpp at times.↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn2"><p>It may be called a function or program. Not really sure.↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn3"><p>I never learned Matlab.↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn4"><p>I will admit, I don’t know what I am doing when benchmarking these functions, but based on my experiences, this is true.↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn5"><p>I am still shaky on what each thing does.↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn6"><p>If you don’t have the first line. R will not make it executable, but the function may be utilized by other functions within the cpp file.↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn7"><p>There are occasions where it is not as straight forward.↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn8"><p>You may need to install other software such as rtools40. In linux, I have r-base-dev installed which may solve some of the needed dependencies.↩︎</p></li>
</ol>
</section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>RCPP</category>
  <guid>www.inqs.info/blog/2021-04-20-incorporating-rcpp/index.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Sat, 01 May 2021 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="www.inqs.info/blog/2021-04-20-incorporating-rcpp/BB2.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Rcpp and Research</title>
  <dc:creator>Isaac Quintanilla</dc:creator>
  <link>www.inqs.info/blog/2021-04-15-rcpp-and-research/index.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 



<p>This is the first post of my “Rcpp” collection detailing my journey with Rcpp. The “Rcpp” collection contains information about the struggles I faced while implementing Rcpp. Even though my first venture to Rcpp happened in the Summer of 2020, I realized I am learning new things every day. I thought it would be wised to write a blog of everything I have and will learn with Rcpp. I hope this collection will guide other students who have never used c++ before.</p>
<p>As I am developing my model for my PhD, a major limiting factor is that my model takes a really long time to compute the results I need. Due to the complexity of the model, I need to approximate different components using iterative algorithms. This in turn increases the computation time to obtain results. You can only imagine my frustration when I first coded my model in R and it took more than a week to obtain results!</p>
<p>Therefore, I decided to focus on speeding up my code. I spent time reading Wickham’s <a href="https://adv-r.hadley.nz/index.html">Advanced R</a> Book to speed up my code. There I learned how about vectorizing code, utilizing built-in optimized functions, and common practices for speed gains. All this work has made me a better R programmer. Unfortunately, when I reran my model, the speed gains was not enough to call my efforts a success.</p>
<p><img src="www.inqs.info/blog/2021-04-15-rcpp-and-research/https:/media.giphy.com/media/Bcpspr9LTSvss/giphy.gif" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p>Due to the lack of improvements, and knowing I will need expand my model for larger data sets, I set on a quest to improve my model. I attacked this problem on two fronts: looking for mathematical methods to reduce my computation needs and implementing different computing techniques. While both components dramatically improved my computational time, implementing c++ via Rcpp was the biggest game changer for my model.</p>
<p>After I implemented everything I can from Wickham’s <a href="https://adv-r.hadley.nz/index.html">Book</a>. I began reading more about about c++ from the book’s <a href="https://adv-r.hadley.nz/rcpp.html">c++ chapter</a>. I will be honest, I didn’t know what I was doing. This was my first time learning how to use c++. Nevertheless, I was determined to learn more about the c++ due to the potential speed gains. During the summer of 2020, I spent all my time learning about c++ and Rcpp. By the end of my summer, a model that took 3.5 days to converge was now taking approximately 6 hours!</p>
<p><img src="www.inqs.info/blog/2021-04-15-rcpp-and-research/https:/media.giphy.com/media/xT0GqssRweIhlz209i/giphy.gif" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p>With this triumph, I have been able to test and diagnose any faults with my model. I can honestly say that implementing Rcpp has drastically improved my PhD experience. I no longer have the feeling of being anxious for days wondering if my model works or not. I feel more productive! With this confidence, I feel prepared to tackle new problems with my research.</p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>RCPP</category>
  <guid>www.inqs.info/blog/2021-04-15-rcpp-and-research/index.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 15 Apr 2021 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="www.inqs.info/blog/2021-04-15-rcpp-and-research/BL3.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Welcome!</title>
  <dc:creator>Isaac Quintanilla Salinas</dc:creator>
  <link>www.inqs.info/blog/welcome/index.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 



<p>Welcome! I’ve decided to create this blog as a way to record my journey in Statistics. As I am working through my PhD, I’ve read numerous posts on vast topics. As I was reading about topics related to Rcpp. I noticed how difficult it was to implement Rcpp for my needs. At the same moment, it dawned on me that I am reading from individuals that at some point in time were struggling with the same issues. This inspired me to create a blog of my own with the same intentions to help other individuals. My hope is to demonstrate how I overcame the challenges I faced to others that are facing similar issues.</p>
<p>I don’t know how this blog will go. It’s going to be a learning experience. I don’t even know how many blog posts I will write in a year. I don’t even know what topics I will write about. However, I hope overtime, I can create a blog that may help people.</p>



 ]]></description>
  <guid>www.inqs.info/blog/welcome/index.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 14 Apr 2021 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="www.inqs.info/blog/welcome/sunset.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
